Guide to the Thomas Hartley Crawford Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Thomas Hartley Crawford papers
1827-1862
MS 844
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.5
The most important part of the Thomas Hartley Crawford Papers relate to Crawford's work on a presidential commission investigating land fraud in connection with the 1832 treaty with the Creek Indians. There are also legal opinions, reports, financial records and correspondence with members of Congress which reflect his work as Commissioner of Indian Affairs, 1836-1845, and as a judge in Washington, D.C., 1845-1861. Among his correspondents are Dixon H. Lewis, C. C. Clay, William Mitchell and J. C. Ten Eyck.
Crawford, Thomas Hartley, 1786-1863
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Charles and Lindley Eberstadt, 1971.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
Thomas Hartley Crawford, a lawyer from Pennsylvania, served as representative to Congress from 1829-1833. In 1836 he was appointed to investigate suspected fraud in the sale of Creek lands in Alabama. From 1838 to 1845 he served as Commissioner of Indian Affairs and subsequently as judge of the criminal court in the District of Columbia, 1845-1861. He died in 1863.
Thomas Hartley Crawford's papers, spanning the years 1827 to 1862, concern both his personal and official affairs, although in both cases they are largely financial and legal in character. The personal papers include a voluminous financial correspondence (1827-1862) with Anna Maria Inglis, the head of a boarding school attended by Crawford's sisters and daughters. There is also a brief autobiographical sketch written in 1858.
The major portion of the papers stems from Crawford's investigative work on the 1832 treaty with the Creek Indians and contains testimony, documents and legal opinions in the case against General James C. Watson. Other papers are connected with Crawford's work as Commisssioner of Indian Affairs, including his legal opinions on cases concerning Indian lands (1838), miscellaneous legal documents, correspondence, accounts and memoranda relating to the Miami Indians (1839-1842). The Shawnee and the Cherokee tribes are also mentioned in several cases. There are a few items concerning local ordinances in Washington (1837-1855).
Biographical / Historical
Thomas Hartley Crawford, a lawyer from Pennsylvania, served as representative to Congress from 1829-1833. He then served as a member of the Pennsylvania State House of Representatives in 1833-1834. In 1836, he was appointed to investigate suspected fraud in the sale of Creek lands in Alabama. From 1838 to 1845 he served as Commissioner of Indian Affairs and subsequently as judge of the criminal court in the District of Columbia, 1845-1861. He died in 1863.
Creek Indians; Education; Indians of North America; Law; Miami Indians; Southern States; Washington (D.C.); Lawyers; Legislators; Politicians; Clay, Clement Comer, 1789-1866; Crawford, Thomas Hartley, 1786-1863; Lewis, Dixon Hall, 1802-1848; Lewis, Ellis, 1798-1871; Livingston, John; Mitchell, William, 1807-1865; Poinsett, Joel Roberts, 1779-1851; Ten Eyck, John C. (John Conover), 1814-1879; United States. Bureau of Indian Affairs
- Inventory
  - Personal papers
    - Personal financial and legal papers, 1831-1851 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Financial correspondence with Anna Maria Inglis, 1827-1862 (Box 1, Folder 2 - 3)
    - Eulogy on Alexander H. Lawrence, 1857 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Autobiographical sketch, 1858 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Professional papers
    - Washington, D.C. - local ordinances and correspondence, 1837-1855 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, 1832-1862 (Box 1, Folder 6 - 7)
    - Indian affairs
      - Legal opinions on cases relating to Indian lands, 1838 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Memoranda, reports, notes and miscellaneous financial and legal documents on Indian affairs, 1840-1842, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Creek Indians
      - Names of towns and Indian chiefs in district of R. W. McHenry, 1836 November (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Legal and financial documents, 1826-1836, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Abstract and notes on testimony of J. C. Watson, 1836 August 26, November 16-17 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Opinion of T. Hartley Crawford on the contract of 1836 Aug 28 between certain Creek chiefs and J. C. Watson, et. al., undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - Copy of the contract approved by the President between certain Creek chiefs and J. C. Watson, 1837 February 17 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Miami Indians: memoranda, correspondence and other papers on the Miami Indians, 1839-1842 (Box 1, Folder 15)